A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Thomas Milton Rivers, Biographical Material, Series 6 FA902
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Thomas Milton Rivers, Biographical Material, Series 6
1922-1965
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rivers, Thomas M. (Thomas Milton)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA902
1.14 Cubic Feet 4 boxes and 1 package.
4 boxes and 1 package. (Boxes 1, 2, 3, and 5, Package 1).
Biographical/Historical note
The newly adopted By-Laws of 1953 provided for an elected Vice-President who was a member of the Board of Trustees. Thomas Milton Rivers was elected the first Vice-President of the newly constituted Board of Trustees and served as Director of The Institute, Director of the Department of Laboratories and Director of the Hospital until his retirement in 1955.
August 1955 amendments to the By-Laws abolished the elected Vice-President and the requirement which provided that he be a member of the Board of Trustees and called for one or more appointed Vice-Presidents. Further amendment, January 25, 1956 provided that the Board of Trustees elect one or more Vice-Presidents to discharge such functions as may be assigned to them by the President or by resolution duly accepted at any meeting.
Between 1955 and 1959 Frank Lappin Horsfall, Jr. held the position of Vice-President for Clinical Studies; between 1955 and 1964 Douglas Whitaker served as Vice-President for Administration (between 1961-64 changed to Vice-President for Academic Administration). In 1964/65 Maclyn McCarty was elected Vice-President with special responsibilities in the clinical sciences. He is at the same time, Physician-in-Chief. In 1965 Carl Pfaffmann was elected Vice-President and Professor to develop a program of research and graduate instruction in the behavioral and social sciences. In 1969/70 a third Vice-President was added. This position carries with it the role of Secretary to the Board of Trustees and was filled by Charles Eugene Sunderlin.
In 1972 the University trustees elected Rodney W. Nichols to a new post of Vice-President for Program planning. He had been the first Director of the Office of Program Planning and Development.
In 1973 Albert Gold was named Vice-President for Academic Resources. As Vice-President he also retains his responsibilities relating to Junior faculty (Director of Postdoctoral Affairs) with additional duties in connection with organization, operation and planning at the University.
In 1974, effective September 15, Maclyn McCarty retired as Physician-in-Chief of the Hospital, which post was then filled by Dr. Attalah Kappas.
June 30, 1976 Eugene Sunderlin retired as vice-president of the RU.
June 1978 Dr. Albert Gold resigned from the University and October 1978 Drs. McCarty and Pfaffmann having reached retirement age resigned their positions as Vice-President. Mr. Rodney Nichols was elected to a new position of executive Vice-President and Mr. David J. Lyons was elected to a new position as Vice-President and Controller with new managerial responsibilities.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 341-6
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Other Finding Aids
FA221 Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Thomas Milton Rivers, Administrative Correspondence, Series 2
Arrangement
Rockefeller University records, Vice President, Thomas Milton Rivers is arranged in two series:
Series 2: Administrative Correspondence. Series 6: Biographical Material.
Biographical / Historical
Vice President, 1953-1955.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, memorabilia and biographical materials.
- Biographical Material, 1922-1965; 6
  Biographical/Historical note
  Biographical note
  1888 Born September 3, Jonesboro, Georgia
  1909 A.B. Emory College
  1909-1911 Johns Hopkins Medical School (dropped out because of poor health)
  1911-1913 Assistant pathologist, Santo Tomas Hospital, Panama
  1913 Reentered Medical School (in 3rd year)
  1915 M.D. Johns Hopkins Medical School
  1915-1916 Interne, Medicine, Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore
  1916-1917 Assistant Resident, Pediatrics, Johns Hopkins Hospital
  1917-1918 Resident, Pediatrics, Johns Hopkins Hospital
  1918-1919 1st Lieutenant Medical Corps U.S. Army Special duty with pneumonia commission, empema commission and pneumonia board
  1919-1921 Instructor in Bacteriology, Johns Hopkins University
  1921-1922 Associate in Bacteriology, Johns Hopkins University
  1920-1922 Pathologist, St. Joseph's Hospital, Baltimore
  1922-1925 Associate Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Hospital
  1925-1927 Associate Member RIMR Hospital
  1927-1955 Member RIMR Hospital
  1936 Sc. D. (Hon.) Emory College
  1937-1955 Director Dept. of the Hospital RIMR
  1938 Sc. D. (Hon.) University of Rochester
  1940- Commander Med. Corps. U.S. Navy (retired as Rear Adm. in 1955)
  1955 Member Emeritus Rockefeller University
  1956-1958 Director National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis
  1958 Vice-President for Medical Affairs National Foundation
  1961 Sc. D. The Rockefeller University
  1962 Died May 12. Buried Arlington National Cemetery
  Member of: American Association Advancement of Science, American Society Clinical Investigations (president 1932), Association American Physicians, Interurban Clinical Club (president 1942-1943), American Pediatric Society, American Epidemiological Society, American Society Experimental Pathology, Society American Bacteriologists (president 1934), Harvey Society, American Association Pathologists and Bacteriologists, American Clinical and Climatological Association, National Academy Sciences, American Philosophical Society, Phi Beta Kappa, Alpha Omega, Sigma Nu, Pi Mu
  Thomas Milton Rivers, pediatrician and virologist at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research from 1922-1955 was the discoverer of Bacillus Parainfluenzae and Virus III. He cultivated vaccine virus for human use and carried on researches in bacteriology, viruses and infectious diseases including influenza, chicken-pox, measles, vaccinia, psittacoses, lymphocytic-choriomeningitis. He was the author of numerous papers and editor and contributor of Filterable Viruses (1928) and Viral and Rickettsial Infections of Man, 1948, 1952, 1958.
  Served as:
  1930 Speaker, 3rd International Congress of Cytologists, Amsterdam Delegate and speaker 1st International Congress of Microbiologists, Paris Speaker, 5th International Congress of Botanists, Cambridge, Eng.
  1931 Speaker, British AAS, London
  1934 Lecturer, 5th National Congress of Medicine, Rosario, Arg.
  1936 Delegate, 2nd International Congress Microbiologists, London
  1939 President, 3rd International Congress Microbiologists, New York
  Related Archival Materials note
  From the Library of T.M. Rivers, Presented to The Rockefeller University Archives, by Arthur T. Pearlstein (Most have been integrated into library collection): Baldwin, E., Dynamic aspects of biochemistry, ed. 2, Cambridge, University Press, 1952. Bayless, W.M. Principles of general physiology, ed. 2, London, Longmans, Green. 1920. Bernheim, B.M. Medicine at the crossroads, N.Y. William Morrow, 1959. Boyd, W.C., Fundamentals of immunology, New York, Interscience, 1943. Brennemann, J., ed. Practice of pediatrics v. 1-4, Hagerstown, W.F. Prior, 1937. Cabot, R.C. Physical diagnosis, ed. 4, New York, William Wood, 1909. Carter, R. The gentle legions, New York, Doubleday, 1961. Cohn, A.E. No retreat from reason, New York, Harcourt, Brace, 1931. Coombs, C.F. Rheumatic heart disease, London, Simpkin, Marshall, Hamilton and Kent, 1924. Cushny, A.R. A textbook of pharmacology and therapeutics, ed. 5, New York, Lea & Febiger, 1910. Delafield, F. and Prudden, T.M. A text-book of pathology, ed. 8, New York, William Wood, 1909. Dubos, R.J. Bacterial and mycotic infections of man, Philadelphia, J.B. Lippincott, 1948. Dubos, R.J. The bacterial cell, Cambridge, Harvard UP, 1945. Duncan, I. My life, New York, Boni & Liveright, 1927. Eisendrath, D.N. Surgical diagnosis, ed. 2, Philadelphia, W.B. Saunders, 1909. Emerson, CP. Clinical diagnosis, ed. 3, Philadelphia, J.P. Lippincott, 1911. Ewing, J. Neoplastic diseases, ed. 2, Philadelphia, W.B. Saunders, 1922. Falta, W. The ductless glandular diseases, Philadelphia, P. Blakiston, 1915. Fantham, H.B. & others. The animal parasites of man, New York, William Wood, 1922. Forchheimer, F., ed. Therapeutics of internal diseases, v. 1-4, New York, D. Appleton, 1913. Ford, W.W. Textbook of bacteriology, Philadelphia, W.B. Saunders, 1927. Fosdick, R.B. Chronicle of a generation, New York, Harper, 1958. Garrod, A.E. and others. Diseases of children, London, E. Arnold, 1913. Gaskell, A. What is life?, Springfield, C.C. Thomas, 1928. Green, D.E. & Knox, W.E., eds. Research in medical science, New York, Macmillan, 1950. Harvard University. Notes on the Harvard tercentenary, Cambridge, Harvard UP, 1936. Hawk, P.B. Practical physiological chemistry, ed. 2, Philadelphia, P. Blakiston, 1909. Hess, A.F. Collected writings, v. 1-2, Springfield, C.C. Thomas, 1936. Hirschfelder, A.D. Diseases of the heart and aorta, Philadelphia, J.B. Lippincott, 1910. Holt, L.E. The diseases of infancy and childhood. ed. 6, New York, D. Appleton, 1913. Horsfall, F.L., ed. Diagnosis of viral and rickettsial infections., New York, Columbia UP, 1949. Howell, W.H. A textbook of physiology, ed. 3, Philadelphia, W.B. Saunders, 1909. Jenner, E. The notebook of Edward Jenner, Oxford UP, 1931. Kant, I. Critique of pure reason, rev. ed., New York, Willey, 1900. Kelly, H.A. Medical gynecology, New York, D. Appleton, 1909. Kolle, W. & Wassermann, A. von, eds. Plandbuch der pathogenen Mikroorganismen v. 1-8, Jena, G. Fischer, 1912-1913. Martin, E. Surgical diagnosis, Philadelphia, Lea & Febiger, 1909. Morgan, J.L.R. The elements of physical chemistry, ed. 5, New York, John Wiley, 1914. Neal, J.B. Encephalitis - a clinical study, New York, Grune & Stratton, 1942. Nothnagel's practice. 4 vol., Philadelphia, W.B. Saunders, 1908-1910. Opie, E.L., Blake, F.G., Small, J.C. & Rivers, T.M. Epidemic respiratory disease, ST. Louis, C.V. Mosby, 1921. Paine, T. Age of reason, New York, Willey, 1794. Pfaundler & Schlossmann, A. eds. The diseases of children v. 1-7, Philadelphia, J.B. Lippincott, 1908-1914. Piersol, G.A. Human anatomy, v. 1-2, Philadelphia, J.B. Lippincott, 1908. Rivers, T.M. ed. Filterable viruses, Lane Medical lectures, Stanford, Stanford UP., 1939. Rivers, T.M. & others. Virus diseases, Ithaca, Cornell UP, 1943. Robertson, T.B. Principles of biochemistry, Philadelphia, Lea & Febiger, 1920. Schaeffer, M. & Muckenfuss, R.S. Experimental poliomyelitis, New. York, National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1940. Starr, M.A. Organic and functional nervous diseases, ed. 3, New York, Lea & Febiger, 1909. Stelwagon, H.W. Treatise on diseases of the skin. ed. 7, Philadelphia, W.B. Saunders, 1914. Stewart, P. The diagnosis of nervous diseases, ed. 3, New York, E.B. Treat, 1913. Stimson, L.A. A practical treatise on fractures and dislocations, ed. 6, New York, Lea & Febiger, 1910. Vanderbilt University. Infantile paralysis, New York, National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1941. Wells, B.G. Chemical pathology, ed. 4, Philadelphia, W.B. Saunders, 1920. Williams, J.W. Obstetrics, ed. 2, New York, Appleton, 1911. Woods, H.M. & Russell, W.T. An introduction to medical statistics, London, P.S. King, 1936.
  - Memorabilia, 1.5 Cubic Feet; Three 2.5" Letter boxes, 1 package
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Date received or inventoried: October - December 1976 (from Dr. Pearlstein)
    - Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - NAS Biographical Memoir by Frank L. Horsfall, Jr. 38: 263-294, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Photographs
      - Portrait of TMR at microscope (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Portraits of TMR - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - TMR in WWII uniform (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Groups photos - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - U.S. Naval Medical Research Unit No. 2 Guam (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Group - 1939 World's Fair (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - TMR report, "A Trip to South American" presented 26 Oct 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Miscellany (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Genealogy, 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Holograph account written by mother; includes letters 1935 August 14 and undated. Typescript copy made 1936 April 10: Holograph letter from W.W. Rivers on genealogy 2 genealogical charts
      - Telegram signed "Teresa", 1961 January 23
      - Christmas card (no identification)
      - Winter photo of house (found in Dubos, R. "The Bacterial Cell")
      - Request from National Academy of Sciences for biographical data, 1933
    - Paper weight: Presidential award "International Poliomyelitis Congress" (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Images, 10 pictures (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Pencil self-drawing, initialed T.M.R. (Found in Starr, "Organic and Functional Nervous Disorders"), still image
      - Five young men including T.M. Rivers (appears to be group of cln:: classmates or house staff), still image
      - Photograph of T.M. Rivers, 1927; still image
      - Photograph of T.M. Rivers, 1932; still image
      - Photograph of T.M. Rivers, undated; still image
      - Autographed photo of Anton j. Carlson, 1950; still image
      - Photo of Simon Flexner at desk, still image
      - Photo of house with eight figures on porch (no dates or identification), still image
      - Two glossy prints of January 15, 1957 event, 1957 January 15; still image
      - Apparently taken in U.S. Post Office T.M. Rivers in both; seem. to include Mary Lasker and Basil O'Connor but not positively identified, still image
    - Pages from 1948 National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis Grant Book (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
    - Membership card, 1958 New York State/County Medical Society Program 1954 September 8 III International Poliomyelitis Conference Birthday Memorial "Franklin D. Roosevelt" 75th January 30, 1957, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 75th Conference on Cellular Biology, Nuceic Acids and Viruses: Program, 1957 January 30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Invitation New York Academy of Science dinner in honor of Basil O'Connor and booklet of guests and table arrangements, 1957 January 8 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - University of Rochester 91st Commencement Addresses by Winston Churchill, Eve Curue, Robert P. Peterson, 1941 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Johns Hopkins School of Medicine Class of 1915, 25th Reunion (president: T.M. Rivers), 1940 February 23-24 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Booklet for campaign of National Conference of Christians and Jews with personal note from Basil O'Connor, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Citation from members of New York City Board of Health (includes individual signatures) at time of T.M. Rivers resignation from the Board, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Lantern slides, 3 1/4" × 4" lantern slides (Box 3)
      - Guam, 18, 16, 18 in 3 boxes
        - 7 of sections and chart (not identified), 1 box
        - 6 of sections; 2 charts (not identified), 1 box
      - 22 labeled "Monk TBC" package
      - 18 x-rays Psittacosis marked Dr. Barry package
      - 19 x-rays Psittacosis marked Dr. Barry package
      - 20 Typhus package
    - Third International Congress of Microbiology, 1 volume
      Scope and Contents note
      Report of Proceedings, presented to T.M. Rivers, President of the Congress by his associates of the Executive Committee. Flyleaf bears all signatures, New York, June 1940.
      Separated Materials
      Relocated to RAC Library 8/9/88.
    - Dubos, René. The bacterial cell. Autographed and presented to "Tom Rivers", 1 volume
    - Rivers, Thomas M. Lane Medical lectures: Viruses and virus diseases (Stanford UP publication, 1939) signed "Rivers", 1 volume
    - Virus diseases by members of the RIMR (delivered as the Messenger Lectures at Cornell University, 1942; 1 volume
    - Basil O'Connor 65th birthday: photo, menu, program, 1957 January 8; package, 2 copies (Package 1)
    - Thomas M. Rivers photograph (Harris V. Ewing, Washington, DC, undated; package (Package 1)
    - Thomas M. Rivers photograph (Irving Penn), 1947; package (Package 1)
    - Presidential appointment. 1st Lieutenant in the Medical Section ORC U.S. Army, 1917; package (Package 1)
    - William H. Welch photograph, undated; package (Package 1)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1965; 1 box (2½ inches)
    This group of correspondence was given to the Archives from the Office of Faculty and Student Records and consists, primarily, of correspondence with the Business Manager, Dr. Gasser and a few with Dr. Bronk.
    The correspondence deals with employment matters and appropriations and is a combination which deals with personal as well as administrative matters. Included are some photographs; newspaper items; announcements of appointment as Director of The Rockefeller Institute Hospital and a carbon copy typescript of a portion of the oral history interview conducted by Saul Benison.
    Arrangement note
    Arranged in chronological order.
    Date received or inventoried: June 1980
    - Photographs and curriculum vitae and news items (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1922-1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Biography from National Foundation (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Bibliography (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Typescript of oral interview (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with Mrs. Rivers and photocopy of news items at time of death, 1944-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Collected papers, 4 bound volumes
    BOX 6 NO LONGER EXISTS - VOLUMES RELOCATED TO RAC LIBRARY 8/9/1988.
    - 1916-1929, 1; volume
      Relocated to RAC Library 1988.
    - 1930-1934, 2; volume
    - 1935-1939, 3; volume
    - 1940-1954, 4; volume
    - Rivers, Thomas M., ed. Viral and rickettsial infections of man. Philadelphia, J.B. Lippincott Company, 1948; 1 volume, 587 pp.
      Presented to the Archives by Cynthia H. Pierce.
    - Tom Bensons: reflections on a life in medicine and science, an oral history memoir prepared by Paul Benson, MIT press, 1967, 1 volume
      (moved from R.G 341.6 box 1).
    - Typewritten C.V. with note from Adrienne Barry to Miss Olmstead, circa 1922
      Date is approximate and based on McCartney file, circa 1922.